<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="xfce_input_device_list_private_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2026 Brian Tarricone &lt;brian@tarricone.org&gt;

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
    obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation files
    (the "Software"), to deal in the Software without restriction,
    including without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge,
    publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software,
    and to permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so,
    subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the
    next paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial
    portions of the Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
    EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF
    MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND
    NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS
    BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN
    ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN
    CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE
    SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="xfce_input_device_list_private_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="Input device list">
      This interface provides a global that will list input devices currently
      attached to the system, along with their current and possible settings.

      This interface is informational and read-only: it reports each device's
      settings, their defaults, and the values the device supports, but provides
      no means to change them. Settings are configured through other Xfce
      mechanisms; this protocol reflects the resulting state back to clients.

      It is intended to be private to the Xfce desktop implementation, and
      should not be used by other applications. This protocol may introduce
      incompatible changes at any time, without warning, and without following
      normal, accepted guidelines about Wayland protocol versioning.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the binding to the global">
        Destroys the client's binding to the global. Existing device objects
        are unaffected and remain valid until released.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="device">
      <description summary="new input device">
        Notifies the client of an input device currently attached to the
        system. This event is sent for every device present when the global is
        bound, and again whenever a device is later added.

        The device's name and capabilities are immutable for the lifetime of
        the device and are provided here. Following this event, the compositor
        sends the device's applicable settings on the newly created object
        before sending the next done event.

        A single physical device may expose more than one capability; it is
        always represented by exactly one xfce_input_device_v1 object regardless
        of how many capabilities it has.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="xfce_input_device_v1" summary="the new device object"/>
      <arg name="name" type="string" summary="the (mostly) human-readable device name"/>
      <arg name="capabilities" type="uint" enum="capabilities" summary="bitfield of the device's capabilities"/>
    </event>

    <event name="done">
      <description summary="a batch of newly added devices has been fully sent">
        Sent after the compositor has finished emitting a group of newly added
        devices, including each new device's full set of settings. It is sent
        once after the initial set of devices present when the global was bound,
        and again after each later group of devices is added.

        This event is not sent when the settings of an existing device change;
        such updates are delivered as standalone setting events on the affected
        device object.
      </description>
    </event>

    <enum name="capabilities" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="input device capabilities">
        The kinds of input a device is able to produce. A device may have more
        than one of these set. The values mirror libinput's device
        capabilities.
      </description>
      <entry name="keyboard" value="1" summary="device produces key events"/>
      <entry name="pointer" value="2" summary="device produces relative pointer events (mouse, touchpad, trackpoint)"/>
      <entry name="touch" value="4" summary="device produces touch events (touchscreen)"/>
      <entry name="tablet_tool" value="8" summary="device is a graphics tablet driven by a tool (pen)"/>
      <entry name="tablet_pad" value="16" summary="device is the button pad of a graphics tablet"/>
      <entry name="gesture" value="32" summary="device produces gesture events (pinch, swipe)"/>
      <entry name="switch" value="64" summary="device produces switch events (lid, tablet-mode)"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>

  <interface name="xfce_input_device_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="A single input device">
      Represents a single input device, and exposes the settings the compositor
      is able to apply to it. The device's name and capabilities are immutable
      for the device's lifetime and are provided as arguments of the
      xfce_input_device_list_private_v1.device event that creates this object.

      Immediately after this object is created, the compositor sends one event
      for each setting that is applicable to the device. A setting event is only
      sent when the setting is
      available on the device; the absence of a setting event means the device
      does not support that setting at all. Where a setting is a choice among
      several values, the event also reports which of those values the device
      supports.

      Whenever a setting changes for any reason (for example, the compositor
      applying a new configuration), the corresponding event is sent again with
      an updated current value.
    </description>

    <request name="release" type="destructor">
      <description summary="release the device object">
        Tells the compositor the client will no longer use this object. The
        client should send this after receiving the removed event, but may send
        it at any time if it is no longer interested in the device.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="removed">
      <description summary="device has been removed from the system">
        The device has been removed from the system. No further events will be
        sent on this object; the client should release it.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="send_events">
      <description summary="how the device may be enabled or disabled">
        Reports the device's send-events mode, which controls whether and when
        the device generates input events. This setting is available on every
        device.
      </description>
      <arg name="supported" type="uint" enum="send_events_modes" summary="bitfield of supported values"/>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="send_events_modes" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="send_events_modes" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="accel_speed">
      <description summary="pointer acceleration speed">
        Reports the device's normalized pointer-acceleration speed, in the
        range [-1, 1], where 0 is the device's default acceleration, -1 is the
        slowest, and 1 is the fastest. Only sent for devices that use pointer
        acceleration.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="fixed" summary="default speed, in the range [-1, 1]"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="fixed" summary="current speed, in the range [-1, 1]"/>
    </event>

    <event name="accel_profile">
      <description summary="pointer acceleration profile">
        Reports the device's pointer-acceleration profile, which selects the
        algorithm used to map device movement to pointer movement. Only sent for
        devices that support more than the "none" profile.
      </description>
      <arg name="supported" type="uint" enum="accel_profiles" summary="bitfield of supported values"/>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="accel_profiles" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="accel_profiles" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="natural_scroll">
      <description summary="natural (reverse) scrolling">
        Reports whether natural scrolling is enabled, in which the content
        follows the finger or wheel direction rather than the scroll bar. Only
        sent for devices that support natural scrolling.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="natural_scroll_state" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="natural_scroll_state" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="scroll_method">
      <description summary="how scroll events are produced">
        Reports the method used to turn device movement into scroll events. Only
        sent for devices that support a configurable scroll method.
      </description>
      <arg name="supported" type="uint" enum="scroll_methods" summary="bitfield of supported values"/>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="scroll_methods" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="scroll_methods" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="scroll_button">
      <description summary="button used for on-button-down scrolling">
        Reports the button that, while held, turns device movement into scroll
        events when the on_button_down scroll method is in use. The value is an
        evdev button code, or 0 if button scrolling is disabled. Only sent for
        devices that support the on_button_down scroll method.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" summary="default button code, or 0 if disabled"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" summary="current button code, or 0 if disabled"/>
    </event>

    <event name="scroll_button_lock">
      <description summary="whether the scroll button latches">
        Reports whether the scroll button latches: when enabled, the button is
        pressed and released once to start and stop scrolling rather than being
        held down. Only sent for devices that support the on_button_down scroll
        method.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="scroll_button_lock_state" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="scroll_button_lock_state" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="click_method">
      <description summary="how button clicks are produced">
        Reports the method used to determine which button a click maps to on a
        clickpad, either by the area of the pad pressed or by the number of
        fingers down. Only sent for devices that support a configurable click
        method.
      </description>
      <arg name="supported" type="uint" enum="click_methods" summary="bitfield of supported values"/>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="click_methods" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="click_methods" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="clickfinger_button_map">
      <description summary="finger-count to button mapping for clickfinger">
        Reports how a one-, two-, or three-finger click maps to a logical
        button when the clickfinger click method is in use. Only sent for
        devices that support the clickfinger click method.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="button_map" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="button_map" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="left_handed">
      <description summary="left-handed button layout">
        Reports whether the device's buttons are configured for left-handed use,
        which typically swaps the left and right buttons. Only sent for devices
        that support a left-handed layout.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="left_handed_state" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="left_handed_state" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="middle_emulation">
      <description summary="middle-button emulation">
        Reports whether middle-button emulation is enabled, in which a
        simultaneous left and right button press is reported as a middle button
        press. Only sent for devices that support middle-button emulation.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="middle_emulation_state" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="middle_emulation_state" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="tap">
      <description summary="tap-to-click">
        Reports whether tap-to-click is enabled, in which a tap on the device is
        reported as a button click. Only sent for devices that support
        tap-to-click.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="tap_state" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="tap_state" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="tap_finger_count">
      <description summary="number of fingers usable for tapping">
        Reports the number of fingers that can be detected for tap-to-click on
        the device. This is a fixed property of the device and cannot be
        changed; it is provided so the client knows which tap-related settings
        are meaningful. Only sent for devices that support tap-to-click.
      </description>
      <arg name="count" type="uint" summary="number of tappable fingers"/>
    </event>

    <event name="tap_button_map">
      <description summary="finger-count to button mapping for tapping">
        Reports how a one-, two-, or three-finger tap maps to a logical button.
        Only sent for devices that support tap-to-click.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="button_map" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="button_map" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="tap_drag">
      <description summary="tap-and-drag">
        Reports whether tap-and-drag is enabled, in which a tap followed by a
        finger movement drags with the left button held. Only sent for devices
        that support tap-to-click.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="drag_state" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="drag_state" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="tap_drag_lock">
      <description summary="tap-and-drag lock">
        Reports whether drag lock is enabled for tap-and-drag, in which lifting
        the finger does not immediately end the drag. Only sent for devices that
        support tap-to-click.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="drag_lock_state" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="drag_lock_state" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="three_finger_drag">
      <description summary="three-finger drag">
        Reports whether dragging with three (or four) fingers is enabled, in
        which placing the corresponding number of fingers down and moving drags
        with the left button held. Only sent for devices that support
        three-finger drag.

        The max_fingers argument reports the largest number of fingers the
        device supports for this gesture: if it is 3, only the enabled_3fg value
        is usable; if it is 4, both enabled_3fg and enabled_4fg are usable.
      </description>
      <arg name="max_fingers" type="uint" summary="maximum supported finger count (3 or 4)"/>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="three_finger_drag_state" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="three_finger_drag_state" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="dwt">
      <description summary="disable-while-typing">
        Reports whether disable-while-typing is enabled, in which the device is
        temporarily disabled while a keyboard is being used to avoid spurious
        input. Only sent for devices that support disable-while-typing.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="dwt_state" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="dwt_state" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="dwt_timeout">
      <description summary="disable-while-typing timeout">
        Reports the time, in milliseconds, between the last key event and the
        device being re-enabled when disable-while-typing is active. Only sent
        for devices that support a configurable disable-while-typing timeout.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" summary="default timeout in milliseconds"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" summary="current timeout in milliseconds"/>
    </event>

    <event name="dwtp">
      <description summary="disable-while-trackpointing">
        Reports whether disable-while-trackpointing is enabled, in which the
        device is temporarily disabled while a trackpoint is being used. Only
        sent for devices that support disable-while-trackpointing.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" enum="dwtp_state" summary="default setting value"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" enum="dwtp_state" summary="current setting value"/>
    </event>

    <event name="dwtp_timeout">
      <description summary="disable-while-trackpointing timeout">
        Reports the time, in milliseconds, between the last trackpoint event and
        the device being re-enabled when disable-while-trackpointing is active.
        Only sent for devices that support a configurable
        disable-while-trackpointing timeout.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" summary="default timeout in milliseconds"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" summary="current timeout in milliseconds"/>
    </event>

    <event name="rotation">
      <description summary="rotation applied to device motion">
        Reports the clockwise rotation, in whole degrees in the range [0, 360),
        applied to all motion events from the device. Only sent for devices that
        support rotation.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_value" type="uint" summary="default angle, in degrees clockwise"/>
      <arg name="current_value" type="uint" summary="current angle, in degrees clockwise"/>
    </event>

    <event name="calibration">
      <description summary="calibration matrix for absolute coordinates">
        Reports the calibration matrix applied to the device's absolute
        coordinates, as the six values [a, b, c, d, e, f] forming the first two
        rows of the 3x3 transformation matrix

            [ a  b  c ]
            [ d  e  f ]
            [ 0  0  1 ]

        applied to normalized device coordinates. The identity matrix
        (a=1, e=1, all others 0) represents no calibration. Only sent for
        devices that can be calibrated.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_a" type="fixed" summary="default matrix element a (row 1, col 1)"/>
      <arg name="default_b" type="fixed" summary="default matrix element b (row 1, col 2)"/>
      <arg name="default_c" type="fixed" summary="default matrix element c (row 1, col 3)"/>
      <arg name="default_d" type="fixed" summary="default matrix element d (row 2, col 1)"/>
      <arg name="default_e" type="fixed" summary="default matrix element e (row 2, col 2)"/>
      <arg name="default_f" type="fixed" summary="default matrix element f (row 2, col 3)"/>
      <arg name="current_a" type="fixed" summary="current matrix element a (row 1, col 1)"/>
      <arg name="current_b" type="fixed" summary="current matrix element b (row 1, col 2)"/>
      <arg name="current_c" type="fixed" summary="current matrix element c (row 1, col 3)"/>
      <arg name="current_d" type="fixed" summary="current matrix element d (row 2, col 1)"/>
      <arg name="current_e" type="fixed" summary="current matrix element e (row 2, col 2)"/>
      <arg name="current_f" type="fixed" summary="current matrix element f (row 2, col 3)"/>
    </event>

    <event name="area">
      <description summary="active region of the tablet surface">
        Reports the rectangular sub-region of a graphics tablet's surface that
        is active; tablet-tool input is scaled to this region as if it were the
        full surface. The region is given as the upper-left point (x1, y1) and
        the lower-right point (x2, y2), each normalized to the range [0, 1] as a
        proportion of the device's width and height, so the full surface is
        (0, 0) to (1, 1). The conditions x1 is less than x2 and y1 is less than
        y2 always hold. Only sent for devices that support configuring an active
        area.
      </description>
      <arg name="default_x1" type="fixed" summary="default upper-left x, in the range [0, 1]"/>
      <arg name="default_y1" type="fixed" summary="default upper-left y, in the range [0, 1]"/>
      <arg name="default_x2" type="fixed" summary="default lower-right x, in the range [0, 1]"/>
      <arg name="default_y2" type="fixed" summary="default lower-right y, in the range [0, 1]"/>
      <arg name="current_x1" type="fixed" summary="current upper-left x, in the range [0, 1]"/>
      <arg name="current_y1" type="fixed" summary="current upper-left y, in the range [0, 1]"/>
      <arg name="current_x2" type="fixed" summary="current lower-right x, in the range [0, 1]"/>
      <arg name="current_y2" type="fixed" summary="current lower-right y, in the range [0, 1]"/>
    </event>

    <enum name="natural_scroll_state">
      <description summary="natural scrolling">
        Whether the content follows the finger or wheel direction.
      </description>
      <entry name="disabled" value="0" summary="natural scrolling is disabled"/>
      <entry name="enabled" value="1" summary="natural scrolling is enabled"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="left_handed_state">
      <description summary="left-handed button layout">
        Whether the device's buttons are configured for left-handed use.
      </description>
      <entry name="disabled" value="0" summary="left-handed layout is disabled"/>
      <entry name="enabled" value="1" summary="left-handed layout is enabled"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="send_events_modes" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="when a device generates events">
        Controls whether a device generates input events. The supported argument
        of the send_events event is a bitfield of these values; enabled is
        implicit and always available. The default and current arguments hold a
        single value.
      </description>
      <entry name="enabled" value="0" summary="the device is always enabled"/>
      <entry name="disabled" value="1" summary="the device is disabled"/>
      <entry name="disabled_on_external_mouse" value="2" summary="the device is disabled while an external mouse is attached"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="accel_profiles" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="pointer acceleration profiles">
        The acceleration algorithms a device may use. The supported argument of
        the accel_profile event is a bitfield of these values; the default and
        current arguments hold a single value.
      </description>
      <entry name="none" value="0" summary="no acceleration profile is configurable"/>
      <entry name="flat" value="1" summary="movement is scaled by a constant factor with no acceleration"/>
      <entry name="adaptive" value="2" summary="movement is accelerated based on the device's speed"/>
      <entry name="custom" value="4" summary="movement is mapped by a user-defined acceleration function"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="scroll_methods" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="ways scroll events are produced">
        The methods by which device movement may be turned into scroll events.
        The supported argument of the scroll_method event is a bitfield of these
        values; the default and current arguments hold a single value.
      </description>
      <entry name="no_scroll" value="0" summary="movement never produces scroll events"/>
      <entry name="two_finger" value="1" summary="scrolling occurs when two fingers are down"/>
      <entry name="edge" value="2" summary="scrolling occurs along the bottom or right edge"/>
      <entry name="on_button_down" value="4" summary="scrolling occurs while the scroll button is held"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="scroll_button_lock_state">
      <description summary="scroll button latching">
        Whether the scroll button must be held or latches with a press and
        release.
      </description>
      <entry name="disabled" value="0" summary="the scroll button must be held down to scroll"/>
      <entry name="enabled" value="1" summary="the scroll button latches on and off"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="click_methods" bitfield="true">
      <description summary="ways button clicks are produced on a clickpad">
        The methods by which a clickpad determines which button a click maps to.
        The supported argument of the click_method event is a bitfield of these
        values; the default and current arguments hold a single value.
      </description>
      <entry name="none" value="0" summary="no click method is configurable"/>
      <entry name="button_areas" value="1" summary="the button is chosen by the region of the pad that is pressed"/>
      <entry name="clickfinger" value="2" summary="the button is chosen by the number of fingers down"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="button_map">
      <description summary="finger-count to button mapping">
        How a one-, two-, or three-finger tap or click maps to logical buttons.
        Used by both the tap_button_map and clickfinger_button_map events.
      </description>
      <entry name="lrm" value="0" summary="1/2/3 fingers map to left/right/middle"/>
      <entry name="lmr" value="1" summary="1/2/3 fingers map to left/middle/right"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="middle_emulation_state">
      <description summary="middle-button emulation">
        Whether a simultaneous left and right button press is reported as a
        middle button press.
      </description>
      <entry name="disabled" value="0" summary="middle-button emulation is disabled"/>
      <entry name="enabled" value="1" summary="middle-button emulation is enabled"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="tap_state">
      <description summary="tap-to-click">
        Whether a tap on the device is reported as a button click.
      </description>
      <entry name="disabled" value="0" summary="tap-to-click is disabled"/>
      <entry name="enabled" value="1" summary="tap-to-click is enabled"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="drag_state">
      <description summary="tap-and-drag">
        Whether a tap followed by finger movement drags with the button held.
      </description>
      <entry name="disabled" value="0" summary="tap-and-drag is disabled"/>
      <entry name="enabled" value="1" summary="tap-and-drag is enabled"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="drag_lock_state">
      <description summary="tap-and-drag lock">
        Whether lifting the finger immediately ends a tap-and-drag, and if not,
        how the drag is eventually ended.
      </description>
      <entry name="disabled" value="0" summary="lifting the finger ends the drag immediately"/>
      <entry name="enabled_timeout" value="1" summary="the drag continues until a timeout expires after the finger is lifted"/>
      <entry name="enabled_sticky" value="2" summary="the drag continues until the finger is tapped again"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="three_finger_drag_state">
      <description summary="three-finger drag">
        Whether placing three or four fingers down and moving drags with the
        button held.
      </description>
      <entry name="disabled" value="0" summary="three-finger drag is disabled"/>
      <entry name="enabled_3fg" value="1" summary="dragging is started with three fingers"/>
      <entry name="enabled_4fg" value="2" summary="dragging is started with four fingers"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="dwt_state">
      <description summary="disable-while-typing">
        Whether the device is temporarily disabled while a keyboard is in use.
      </description>
      <entry name="disabled" value="0" summary="disable-while-typing is disabled"/>
      <entry name="enabled" value="1" summary="disable-while-typing is enabled"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="dwtp_state">
      <description summary="disable-while-trackpointing">
        Whether the device is temporarily disabled while a trackpoint is in use.
      </description>
      <entry name="disabled" value="0" summary="disable-while-trackpointing is disabled"/>
      <entry name="enabled" value="1" summary="disable-while-trackpointing is enabled"/>
    </enum>
  </interface>
</protocol>
